[music]
>> Hello and welcome to this video on new
things we added for MCP server in
Business Central.
We have two new things. One is support
for API queries, that's this video, and
then we have opened up for all
Microsoft's APIs, that's in the other
video. I hope you will watch both of
them.
Now, to give some context of the
business value of of API queries in MCP
server,
um think about the investment we did in
Power BI. We added Power BI apps for
most functional areas in Business
Central, and the foundation, the data
foundation for these reports or apps uh
API queries. Those API queries are now
also available for your external agents.
So, if you want to include things like
aggregations or analytics,
these APIs were designed for just that
and have also great documentation for
your agent to know how to use them.
In the release wave one for Business
Central here in 2026,
uh highlighted in italic, you can see
what we already shipped in April, and we
now have in in version 22
28.2 two new things, support for API API
queries, this video, and support for all
APIs, the next video.
Let's dive in to see how you enable API
queries.
As I mentioned, API queries are the
foundation for our Power BI apps, and
this is now available in Business
Central uh MCP server. Let me show you
how that works.
I have um
here a
MCP server configuration,
and if I go down here under object type
and choose query, when I then choose the
dot dot dot ellipsis for object ID,
you can see we now open up for all those
great APIs. I just scroll down to
the ones on Power BI here. So, GL
account category, anything related to
finance, anything related to inventory
and so on. These are all grouped under
the API group analytics. And even though
they show version 0.5 and version 1 is
just for backwards compatibility,
we will choose the the the highest
number of the API.
And that's really what there is to it
inside the MCP server. Like the cool
part is now for you to go and utilize
this to make your agents much better and
for analytics. And to help you with
that,
our documentation for the APIs are here.
This short URL, aka.ms/bcintegration.
And if you zoom down under APIs,
down here, you can see the analytics API
reference has kind of for all these
APIs, they are documented there.
That's nice, but we even took it further
and documented where in our Power BI
apps are these APIs used. So, here you
can see the section Power BI apps and
the analytics APIs. You can actually see
the semantic models that we have
documented for Power BI are sure
those documentation articles show
exactly how these APIs are used and the
types of calculations we do in Power BI
to make all the KPIs. So, you can
probably even use that reference as
instructions or knowledge to your
agents. Maybe you want to point to that
in Co-pilot Studio to give your agent
better understanding of types of KPIs
and how they are calculated.
And then we also in this article added
for each of the APIs that we now open up
for. Like what is it what type of an
analysis would it be useful whether it's
manufacturing, whether it's sales,
finance or even
combinations or
both some of these APIs are used in
multiple areas.
That's it. If you want to know more
about our investments in MCP server,
there's a full playlist for this. So you
find that under
Then you go to playlist and find the
getting started with MCP server.
That's where you find this video and all
the other videos we made for MCP server.
If you want to know more in general
about MCP server, our documentation also
has this aka link aka.ms/bc
mcp and this is where you find all the
documentation on how configurations work
and and that.
Now before you go to docs or MS learn
and learn everything, make sure that you
just spend the 5 minutes watching the
other video for opening up for all APIs
and then go party on everything in MCP
server. You find that video linked here
and also in the playlist for everything
for MCP server.
That's all for now. Have a great day.
Thank you.